Mannes - Damrosch Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Mannes - Damrosch Collection1848-1986 (bulk 1900-1950)
ML31.M2135
Mannes, David, 1866-1959
circa 1,700 items 36 containers 12 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, music, programs, clippings, artwork, photographs, awards, and other materials. Biographical materials include a copy of autobiography of Leopold Damrosch and memoirs of Marie von Heimburg, the aunt of Clara, Frank, and Walter Damrosch. Both items also exist in Damrosch-Tee Van Collection and Damrosch-Blaine Collection. The correspondence consists of letters between members of the Mannes and Damrosch families and other important correspondents, including Percy Goetschius, Franz Lizst (translation from the original), Daniel Gregory Mason, Sergei Rachmaninoff, John D. Rockefeller, Arthur Schnabel, Randall Thompson, and others. The writings contain primarily numerous literary works by Marya Mannes and articles by Leopold Damrosch, Clara Damrosch Mannes, Leopold Mannes. The music consists of holograph scores, parts, and sketches of compositions by Leopold Damrosch. Also included are manuscript copies of works by Heinrich Gottwald, holograph scores of Edmund Singer, and of songs by Leopold Mannes. The Photographs consist of photoprints and 27 albums of photoprints chiefly related to Mannes and Damrosch families. The artwork includes portraits of various members of the Mannes and Damrosch families, sketches by Clara Damrosch Mannes, and photographic reproductions of sculptures of Marya Mannes.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Damrosch, Leopold, 1832-1885--Correspondence.; Damrosch, Leopold, 1832-1885.; Damrosch, Leopold, 1832-1885. Mannes - Damrosch collection. 1948-1986.; Goetschius, Percy, 1853-1943--Correspondence.; Goetschius, Percy, 1853-1943.; Mannes, Clara, 1869-1948--Correspondence; Mannes, Clara, 1869-1948.; Mannes, Clara, 1869-1948.; Mannes, Clara, 1869-1948. Mannes - Damrosch collection. 1948-1986.; Mannes, David, 1866-1959--Correspondence.; Mannes, David, 1866-1959.; Mannes, David, 1866-1959.; Mannes, Leopold, 1899-1964--Correspondence.; Mannes, Leopold, 1899-1964.; Mannes, Marya.; Rockefeller, John D., 1906-1978--Correspondence.; Rockefeller, John D., 1906-1978.; Schnabel, Artur, 1882-1951--Correspondence.; Schnabel, Artur, 1882-1951.; Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984--Correspondence.; Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984.
Subjects
Musicians--United States--Correspondence.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Marya Mannes and David Blow; 1966 and 1990-1991.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
Two other related collections in the Music Division at the Library of Congress include the Damrosch-Blaine Collection from the Walter Damrosch family and the Damrosch-Tee Van Collection from the Frank Damrosch family, both brothers of Clara Damrosch Mannes. Additionally, both published and unpublished music and/or published writings by Leopold, Walter, and Frank Damrosch, David and Clara Mannes, and Leopold and Marya Mannes have been classified and placed in the general collections of the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The Mannes - Damrosch Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketches
David Mannes was born February 16, 1866 in New York City. He studied the violin at a very early age, and formal lessons soon followed with August Zeiss, a pupil of Ludwig Spohr, and with Carl Richter Nicolai, concertmaster of the Philharmonic Orchestra. Mannes studied later at the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin with the Joachim Quartet's Heinrich de Ahna and with Carl Nadir, assistant to Joseph Joachim, who was a professor of violin at the Hochschule. In 1891, Mannes became a member of the New York Symphony Orchestra under Walter Damrosch; thirteen years later, he became the orchestra's concertmaster, a position he held until he resigned in 1912. He married pianist Clara Damrosch (sister of Walter) in 1898, and their first child, Leopold Damrosch Mannes, was born in 1899. In 1900, David began teaching violin at the Music School Settlement (later the Third Street Music School Settlement) for young, underprivileged children and amateurs. Accompanied by his wife and son, he went to Brussels in 1903 where he studied violin with Eugène Ysaÿe for six months. Once back in the United States, David and Clara began a thirteen-year professional collaboration in 1904 and toured as the Mannes Duo for violin and piano. Later that fall, their second child, Marya, was born. David became musical director at the Music School Settlement in 1910, and in 1912, inaugurated a similar school—the Music School Settlement for Colored Children—in Harlem, assisted by prominent, interested friends from the community. In 1915, Mannes resigned as director of the Third Street Settlement School and also ended his relationship with the Music School Settlement for Colored Children. The following year, he and his wife co-founded the David Mannes School of Music (later to become the Mannes College of Music), which developed potential professional musicians and offered opportunities to those who wanted "to enrich themselves through a better understanding or playing of music without the responsibilities of a career." The final tour of the Mannes Duo occurred during 1916-17, but the couple continued to perform locally until the mid-1920s. After years of intermittent assignments leading an orchestra at the Metropolitan Museum of Art for special occasions, David received a chance to conduct an annual series of free concerts at the Museum which continued for twenty-eight years until 1948. On April 16, 1956 a concert was held there to celebrate David Mannes's ninetieth birthday and to raise funds for the Mannes College of Music. His autobiography, Music Is My Faith, was published in 1938. He died in New York City on April 25, 1959.
Leopold Damrosch (1832-1885), the family patriarch, was a violinist, conductor, and composer who was educated in Posen, his native city, and in Berlin. The Damrosch family—Leopold and Helene von Heimburg Damrosch, their four children, Frank, Walter, Marie and Clara (the fifth and last child, Elizabeth, was born in America), and Helene's sister Marie von Heimburg—immigrated to America from Breslau in 1871. He came to America in 1871 to conduct the Arion Society, a men's choral group; later, in 1873, he founded the Oratorio Society of New York and, in 1878, the Symphony Society of New York. He introduced Wagner operas to America and other large choral works, many of which were American premieres. Both Frank Damrosch (1859-1937) and Walter Damrosch (1862-1950) also contributed to the musical life of New York City. Frank conducted the People's Choral Union, the Oratorio Society of New York, and the Musical Art Society and was founder of the Institute of Musical Arts; Walter conducted operas, particularly Wagner operas, the New York Symphony Society (formerly the Symphony Society of New York), and the NBC Symphony Orchestra in the "Music Appreciation Hour" radio show.
Clara Damrosch Mannes was born on December 12, 1869 in Breslau, Germany. Clara was the middle daughter and the only daughter to pursue a music career. She began piano lessons as a child in New York City; in 1888, she studied piano in Dresden with H. Scholtz and theory with Johannes Schreyer; and, in 1897, she took piano lessons from Ferruccio Busoni in Berlin. David Mannes proposed to Clara in Europe during the summer of 1897 and the following June, they were married. A year later, their son Leopold Damrosch Mannes was born. (A daughter, Marya, arrived in 1904.) While in Brussels in 1903, Clara learned piano parts to various violin sonatas, and on their return to the United States, the couple began a successful career as the Mannes Duo for violin and piano, which performed until the mid-1920s. During the winter of 1915-16, David and Clara prepared for the inauguration of their new school, the David Mannes School of Music, which opened in the fall of 1916. From the very beginning, Clara was responsible for most of the administrative work, taught advanced chamber music students, and supervised the ensemble department. She continued in different capacities at the school for the rest of her life. She died in New York City on March 16, 1947.
Leopold Damrosch Mannes, who inherited the position of director of the Mannes College of Music from his parents, became president of the school in 1950. Born December 26, 1899 in New York City and named after Clara's father, Leopold displayed an early precocity in music. When Ysaÿe heard the youngster perform in Brussels in 1903, the illustrious elder musician remarked that Leopold must be "the reincarnation of Mozart." Leopold Mannes studied piano with Elizabeth Quaile; he also learned composition from Rosario Scalero at the Mannes School and from Percy Goetschius at the Institute of Musical Arts, founded by his uncle, Frank Damrosch. Leopold's interest in music waned during his teens, however, when he developed an interest in photography. He graduated from Harvard University in 1920 after three years of study. Subsequently, he went to Paris where he studied piano with Alfred Cortot. In 1925, Mannes won a Pulitzer scholarship for composition, and later in 1926, a Guggenheim Fellowship. That same year, he married Edith Vernon Simonds, and they lived in Rome during Leopold's eighteen-month fellowship. On their return to America, Leopold taught theory at the Mannes School and at the Institute of Musical Arts. In 1916, Leopold had met Leopold Godowsky, then an underclassman at the Riverdale Country School. Both Leopolds moved to Rochester, New York in 1930 to work at the Eastman Kodak Company after many years of trying independently to invent a color process in photography. In 1935, they completed the development of the Kodachrome process. Leopold divorced Edith Simonds in 1933, and he remained at Rochester until the end of 1939, after which he resumed his musical life in New York City, where he became associate director of the Mannes School of Music the next year. In the summer of 1940, he married Evelyn Sabin, a dancer who studied with Martha Graham at the Eastman School of Music and who danced in the original Martha Graham Trio. In 1948, Leopold established the Mannes Trio (piano, violin and cello) which performed in New York City until 1955. He became president of the Mannes School in 1950, and in 1953, he oversaw the conversion of the school to the Mannes College of Music, which became accredited and began to offer degrees. Leopold Mannes died on August 11, 1964 on Martha's Vineyard.
Marya Mannes was born in New York City on November 14, 1904. Although she came from a musical family, she preferred to be a writer and developed her talent at Miss Veltin's School for Girls. After graduation in 1923, Marya went to Europe where she studied sculpture in London, followed by a resumption of her writing. She returned to New York a year later, and worked further on her writing, which included plays, one of which was produced in 1925. During this time, she met the artist and scenic designer Jo Mielziner, whom she married on March 31, 1926 (and divorced in 1931). In 1930, one of her plays, Café, opened on Broadway, but closed after four days. A short time later, she was engaged by Vogue magazine, first as a copy writer and later as an editor until 1936, when she left for Europe where she eventually married her second husband Richard Blow in 1937. She returned to sculpting activities, which included bronze portraits of Walter Damrosch, Sergei Rachmaninoff, and Raoul de Roussy de Sales. Because of the escalating political turmoil in Europe in 1939, the couple returned to the United States; her only child, David Blow, was born in the same year. During WWII, Marya worked for the Office of War Information and for the Office of Strategic Services. For the latter, she briefly lived in Madrid, also writing articles for Vogue and The New Yorker. Marya divorced Richard Blow in 1943. After the War, she wrote features for Glamour magazine, leaving after a year to complete her first novel, Message from a Stranger, published in 1948. During that same year, she married Christopher Clarkson, who was a British civil air attaché. (They divorced in 1966.) After four years in Washington, DC, Marya and Christopher returned to New York in 1952, where she joined the staff of The Reporter. She remained with the magazine for twelve years writing television, theater, and social criticisms, other articles, and verses, frequently under the pen name SEC. She published three books: More in Anger (1958), The New York I Know (1961), and But Will It Sell? (1964), all of which contained her previously-released essays from various magazines and newspapers. Marya also published a collection of poems, Subverse: Rhymes for Our Times in 1959 and her second novel, They, in 1968. She continued to publish books; her autobiography Out of My Time in 1970; Uncoupling: The Art of Coming Apart with Norman Sheresky in 1973; and Last Rights, dated 1974, based in part from her and Leopold's experiences with the death of their father, David Mannes. Her final tome, The Best of Marya Mannes, an anthology of her writings edited by Robert Mottley, was published in 1986. She moved to San Francisco in 1983 to be near her son David Blow, and died there on September 13, 1990.
Scope and Content Note
The Mannes-Damrosch Collection comprises correspondence and other materials from the Mannes family—David and Clara Damrosch Mannes and their children Leopold and Marya Mannes—and members of the Damrosch family including Leopold Damrosch and his sons, Frank and Walter Damrosch. The collection spans 1848-1986, with the majority of the materials dating from 1900-1950. It includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, music, programs, clippings, artwork, photographs, awards, and other materials.
The Biographical materials include a copy of "The Autobiography of Leopold Damrosch," written when he was eighteen and living in Posen, and "Tante's Story," written by Marie von Heimburg, the aunt of Clara, Frank, and Walter Damrosch who helped raise them and the Mannes' children. These two documents exist also in the other two Damrosch collections in the Music Division. The remaining items include an incomplete biography of Clara Damrosch Mannes and an article written by Leopold Mannes about his trip to Europe in the summer of 1921.
The Correspondence consists of letters written between members of the Mannes and Damrosch families and by others to both families. Some important correspondents include Percy Goetschius, Franz Liszt (only a translation from the original), Daniel Gregory Mason, Sergei Rachmaninoff, John D. Rockefeller, Artur Schnabel, Johannes Schreyer, Randall Thompson, and James Thurber.
The Writings contain primarily stories, poems, and essays by Marya Mannes. A large number of the poems are signed "Sec," which was her pen name she used at The Reporter. Also, included are articles by Leopold Damrosch, Clara Damrosch Mannes, Leopold Mannes, and an untitled speech by David Mannes.
The Music consists chiefly of holograph scores, parts and sketches of compositions by Leopold Damrosch and of arrangements or transcriptions by him. Included are many songs, violin and vocal works, a music sketch of the Vorspiel that Leopold composed on Johann Crüger's chorale, Ich singe dir mit Herz und Mund and which he presented to his wife for their twenty-fifth wedding anniversary, the holograph full score of National Ode, also known as the Centennial Ode, and of his opera Romeo und Julie. Also included are manuscript copies of works by Heinrich Gottwald, holograph scores of Edmund Singer, and of songs by Leopold Mannes.
The Photographs consist of photoprints and twenty-seven albums of photoprints. Possibly, the quantity of the photographic materials is directly related to Leopold Mannes' early interest in photography. He and Leopold Godowsky conducted experiments for many years to develop a color process which eventually resulted in the co-invention of the Kodachrome process at the Eastman Kodak Company in Rochester, New York. The photoprints extend primarily to David and Clara Mannes and their children and the first and second generations of the Damrosch family. The photographic albums primarily center on the Mannes family, especially family vacations including Mannesden, the Mannes' summer home on Lake Champlain, and travels in the United States, Cuba and Europe. Two albums contain photoprints by Leopold Mannes in 1938 of his father conducting an orchestra at the free Museum Concerts which David Mannes presented at the Metropolitan Museum of Art for twenty-eight years until 1947.
The Artwork in the collection includes portraits of various members of the Mannes and Damrosch families and numerous miscellaneous subjects. The engraving plate of a portrait of Leopold Damrosch and two photogravure plates of portraits of David Mannes with his violin are included. Many sketches by Clara Damrosch Mannes, who displayed a talent for art as well as music, are represented. Most likely, a significant number of the unidentified works are by her also. Among the pencil sketches are drawings of Alfred Cortot, with whom Leopold Mannes studied piano in Paris. The sculptures of Mayra Mannes are represented by photographic reproductions, one of which is of her uncle, Walter Damrosch.
Other materials included are: some financial and legal documents; programs from performances by Clara and David Mannes, David Mannes, and Leopold Mannes; clippings pertaining to Leopold and Walter Damrosch, David and Clara Mannes and their children, Leopold and Marya; two scrapbooks, one of which was for David Mannes' 90th birthday; awards primarily given to Marya Mannes; subject files, one of which pertains to David Mannes' involvement in the Music School Settlement for Colored People which he founded; and a few other miscellaneous items.
Margaret Collins, January 1995
Wilda M. Heiss, revised March 1997
Organization of the Mannes - Damrosch Collection
The Mannes - Damrosch Collection is organized in 13 series:
Biographical
Correspondence
Writings
Music
Financial / Legal
Programs
Scrapbooks
Clippings
Photographs
Artwork
Awards
Subject File
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006568218
Container List
- Biographical (Box 1)
  Biographical materials consist of manuscripts and typescripts written by members of the Damrosch and Mannes families.
  Arranged alphabetically by author, then by title
  - Damrosch, Leopold
    - The autobiography of Leopold Damrosch, n.d. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Heimburg, Marie von
    - Tante's story, n.d. (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Mannes, Clara Damrosch
    - [Chronologies], 1914, n.d. (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. [carbons] (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Mannes, Leopold
    - Trip to Europe 1921 (Summer) (Box-folder 1/6)
- Correspondence, 1848-1964 and undated (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence consists of letters written to and from Damrosch and Mannes family members and by others to members of both families, a few in translation only.
  Arranged alphabetically by author, then chronologically
  - Birthday Tributes on David Mannes' 90th, 1956 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Blow, David, 1945-47 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Blow, Richard, n.d. (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Brandt, Marianne, 1921 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Chinese Embassy, 1940 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Clarkson, Christopher, 1944 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Condolence letters on Leopold Mannes' death, 1964 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Damrosch, Frank, n.d. (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Damrosch, Helene von Heimburg, 1874-81, n.d. (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Damrosch, Hetty Mosenthal, n.d. (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Damrosch, Leopold
    - 1872 [translation, original in Damrosch-Tee Van Collection] (Box-folder 1/17)
    - 1876-80 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1874-1946, n.d. (Box-folder 1/19)
  - De Roussy de Sales, Raoul, 1931-42, n.d. (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Goetschius, Percy, 1912 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Heimburg, Gisela von, 1848-51 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Heimburg, Marie von, 1912-25, n.d. (Box-folder 1/23)
  - [Heimburg, Nellie von?] Tante Nellie, 1926-35 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Liszt, Franz, 1857 [translation] (Box-folder 1/25)
  - MacKenzie, Colin, 1940, n.d. (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Mannes, Clara Damrosch
    - 1886-89 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - 1900-24 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - 1930-36 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - 1942-48 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Undated (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Mannes, David
    - 1910-19 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - 1934-51 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Mannes, Edith Simonds, 1926-29, n.d. (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Mannes, Evelyn Sabin, 1947 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Mannes, Leopold
    - 1905-18, n.d. (Box-folder 2/6)
    - 1926 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - 1927 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Mannes, Marya
    - 1914-1918, n.d. (Box-folder 2/10)
    - 1921-26 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - 1927-29 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - 1930-45 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - 1947-51 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1928 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Mason, Gregory, 1958 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Mielziner, Jo, 1925, n.d. (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1899-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 2/19)
    - To Marya Mannes, 1938-59, n.d. (Box-folder 2/20)
    - To Marya Mannes (fan mail), 1954-59, n.d. (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Pinsent, Cecil, 1940-42 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1942 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Resman, M. L., 1942 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Rockefeller, John D. 1937, 1947 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Schnabel, Artur, n.d. (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Schreyer, Johannes, 1912-27 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Seymour, Clair, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Seymour, Elizabeth Damrosch
    - 1888-89 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - 1914-51, n.d. (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Sperber, Harry N., 1942-43, n.d. (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Tee Van, Helen Damrosch, 1947 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Thompson, Randall, 1928-64 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Thurber, James, 1959 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Unidentified
    - 1900-48, n.d. (Box-folder 3/8)
    - To Marya Mannes, 1947-58, n.d. (Box-folder 3/9)
    - To Marya Mannes (fan mail), n.d. (Box-folder 3/10)
    - From the Mannes' cat (signed "Puff"), n.d. (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Weichmann, Marie Damrosch, 1899, n.d. (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Wood, Robert Williams, 1935-38 (Box-folder 3/13)
- Writings, 1876-1956 and undated, bulk 1946-56 (Box 3-4)
  Writings consist of manuscripts, typescripts and one printed book written by members of both the Damrosch and Mannes families.
  - Damrosch, Leopold
    - Twilight of the gods, 1876 Sept. 3 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - The Wagner festival, 1876 Aug. 23 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Wagner's musical drama, 1876 Aug. 26 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Mannes, Clara Damrosch
    - Annual Meeting of the Federation for Child Study, 1915 Nov. 3 [speech] (Box-folder 3/17)
    - History of Venice, 1885-1886 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Ideal musical food for the young, 1914 May 16 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - The pauperizing of the music student, n.d. (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Mannes, David
    - Untitled speech, n.d. (Box-folder 3/21)
  - [Mannes, Leopold?]
    - Does science lead us to a true Christianity?, n.d. (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Mannes, Marya
    - Bad men, n.d. (Box-folder 3/23)